What we have just seen is called a
Pshare predictor. It has a private
history for each branch. That is each
branch should have its own history in
the branch history table and it has
shared counters so that different
histories and different branches might
map to the same counters. This predictor
is good for things like even odd
behavior like taken not taken loops with
few iterations. For example, those eight
iteration loops that we have seen and so
on. So pretty much whenever the branch's
own previous behavior is predictive of
its future behavior, Pshare tends to do
well. Another type of similar predictor
that we can make is called G-share. It
has a global history and shared
counters. So a global history means that
there is only a single global history
that we use to predict all branches. So
what we have is now the PC a single
history that we exert together and index
into the array of two bit counters. This
history every branch decision regardless
of what the PC of the branch is gets
shifted in here. So what is Gshshire
good for? It's good for so-called
correlated branches. That is branches
whose decision is related to what the
other branches in the program were
doing. Now I would think when would that
happen and it turns out that it happens
in programs quite often. Think about
something like this. If my shape is a
square then do something. Then do
something that you do either way
regardless of what the shape is. Then if
the shape is not square I have something
else to do. This branch and this branch
are entirely correlated. If this one was
taken this one will not be taken and the
other way around. So if this branch is
in the history when this one is being
predicted then we can perfectly predict
this branch. Note that however if we
look at this branch individually or this
branch individually the history of this
branch might be completely random
because it really depends on our data
whether shapes are squares. So if we
randomly have shapes that are squares or
not, we cannot really predict much here.
So this branch might be mispredicted
often because we simply don't know at
that point. But this branch becomes
perfectly predictable if it's using the
history produced by this branch.